A Guide to the Virginia Wildland Firefighters Oral Histories, 2006: SdArch 32
Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University
Virginia Wildland Firefighters Oral Histories
2006
Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University
DeHart
SdArch 32
243
.05 cubic feet; 10 audiocassettes
The Virginia Wildland Firefighters Oral Histories, 2006, is comprised of three sound recordings of interviews with US Forest Service Fire Fighters on their experiences fighting fires in the mountain region of Virginia, from 1940-2005. The collection includes transcripts, photographs, and other supplemental documents.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Access to oral histories is governed by agreements with the interviewees. Collection open to research. Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection. Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the James Madison University Special Collections Library to use this collection.
Bio/Historical Note
Carol DeHart is a freelance writer and independent scholar from Fulks Run, Virginia. Carol DeHart wasa Fire Instructor and Emergency Medical Technician, and is a charter (1987) member of the Bergton Volunteer Fire Department, and former squad boss and fire line EMT with the US Forest Service. Between 2001-2006, she conducted three grants from James Madison University Library to record and transcribe nine oral history interviews, including the Fading Rural Lifeways in the Bergton/Criders area of Rockingham County Oral History Project (SdArch 26) and the John Stewart Oral History (SdArch 25). In 2010, she completed an interview with Broadway Firefighter (SdArch 39).
Gerald Fawley was the first USFS employee to staff the High Knob Fire Tower on Shenandoah Mountain. He currently resides in Parnassus, Virginia. Wade Rogers is a retired USFS Fire Manager Officer from Spring Creek, Virginia. John Coleman is a retired USFS District Ranger from Edinburg, Virginia. Kenny May is a retired USFS Timer Specialist and Fire Fighter from Bergton, Vriginia. Terry Slater, who assisted DeHart in the interview with Fawley, is a USFS Wildlife Biologist and Incident Commander from Bridgewater, Virginia.
Scope and Content
The interviews focus on wildland fire fighting and the US Forest Service experiences from 1940 through 2005. Topics addressed in the interviews include memories of fire towers, early communications, tools, clothing, transportation, family life, fire-fighting techniques and stories.
Arrangement
The interviews are arranged chronologically, by the date of the interview.
Bibliography
Gingrich, Tyler and Caroline Whitlow. "High Knob Fire Tower." Friends of Shenandoah Mountain: Exploring Shenandoah Mountain's History. Accessed July 24, 2018. http://www.friendsofshenandoahmountain.org/history-of-high-knob-fire-tower.html
- 32-1: Wade Kermit Rogers, interviewed by Carol M. DeHart, February 7, 2006
  Scope and Content
  This interview records the reflections of Wake Kermit Rogers, his life and work with the U.S. Forest Service as a Fire Tower Lookout man, Timber Technician and Fire Management Officer from 1962-1994. Transcription includes text of Psalm 121 with signature by interviewee.
  - Transcript and Supporting Documents, February 7, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Original audiocassette #1, February 7. 2006 (Box 1, Audiocassette SA032-CS-001)
  - Original audiocassette #2, February 7, 2006 (Box 1, Audiocassette SA032-CS-002)
  - Original audiocassette #3, February 7, 2006 (Box 1, Audiocassette SA032-CS-003)
- 32-2: Gerald F. Fawley, interviewed by Carol M. DeHart, January 10, 2006
  This interview records the reflections of Gerald E. Fawley, his life and work staffing the fire towers. Transcription includes appendix with the following contents: A lookout tower man reminisces; Sibley stove and tent notes; Osborne fire finder; Remembrances; 1930's photographs; High Knob Fire Tower notes; 2006 photographs.
  - Transcript and Supporting Documents, January 10, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Original audiocassette #1, January 10, 2006 (Box 1, Audiocassette SA032-CS-004)
  - Original audiocassette #2, January 10, 2006 (Box 1, Audiocassette SA032-CS-005)
  - Original audiocassette #3, January 10, 2006 (Box 1, Audiocassette SA032-CS-006)
- 32-3: Kenny May and Wade Kermit Rogers, interviewed by Carol M. DeHart, undated
  Scope and Contents
  This interview records the reflections of Kenny May and John Coleman, talking about their U.S. Forest Service and fire fighting experiences. Within introduction of transcript, "John William Coleman, [retired District Ranger, Lee Ranger District, Type II Incident Commander, 1957-1998] and Kenneth Edward May [Timber Sale Administrator, 1965-2006]". Transcription includes appendix with the following contents: Kenny May, photos, article and notes, "Notice to Loggers," Fire Tower Log; John Coleman Award article, poster in Lee District work center, reprint newspaper photo, two poems and "Diary of a Fire"; Article: "The Fire Warden System on the Shenandoah" by Helen Gordon, 1929.
  - Transcript and Supporting Documents, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Original audiocassette #1, January 17, 2006 (Box 1, Audiocassette SA032-CS-007)
  - Original audiocassette #2, January 17, 2006 (Box 1, Audiocassette SA032-CS-008)
  - Original audiocassette #3, January 17, 2006 (Box 1, Audiocassette SA032-CS-009)
  - Original audiocassette #4, January 17, 2006 (Box 1, Audiocassette SA032-CS-010)